Nicholas Hoyt

User Experience Designer

Address: Urbana, Illinois, USA Phone:
Portfolio: https://nicholashoyt.com/portfolio Email:

With over 20 years of user interface and interaction design experience, my professionalism and track record of success are based on utilizing design methodologies that focus on users' mental models and usage contexts. This results in a deeper understanding of users' goals, which drives the feature set and task flow design of the product.

Experience

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Sept. 2005 – present

Served as lead interaction and user interface designer, as well as co-developer, of web applications and browser tools focused on web accessibility evaluation.

Several of these tools have been adopted by the University of Illinois and other large university systems (e.g. Penn. State, Indiana University, Ohio State, University of Iowa) as their tools of choice for web accessibility evaluation.

- Designed and co-developed the Functional Accessibility Evaluator, a web application that spiders web sites and produces site-wide reports on WCAG compliance.
- Designed and co-developed the Alnspector for Firefox browser extension, which does the same type of evaluation as FAE for a single web page.
- Designed and developed two additional browser extensions: SkipTo Landmarks & Headings and Page Structure.
- Designed and co-developed the A11yFirst plugins for CKEditor, which provide proactive guidance for accessible authoring
- · Designed and co-developed the Accessibility Bookmarklets, easily installable in any browser.

Independent Contractor, Chicago, IL

Aug. 1999 - Sept. 2005

As owner and principal consultant of Web UI, Inc., provided software design and development services with an emphasis on interaction design and front-end development for various clients, including ABN AMRO, Accenture, Allstate Insurance, Bank One, Fidelity Investments, HOLT Value Associates and the Illinois Institute of Technology.

- · Updated the Contribution Calculator I had previously designed and developed for Fidelity Investments.
- · Authored an ebook on XML and XSLT development for internal use by Accenture developers.
- Designed a web application for use by call center representatives at Allstate Insurance.
- · Designed the user interface of a Java application for use by financial portolio managers for HOLT Value Associates.

Fidelity Investments, Boston, MA

Aug. 1997 - Aug. 1999

Served as lead interaction designer in the redesign of NetBenefits, a web application providing retirement savings account access to over one million customers. Improved the user experience through contextual inquiry, task flow analysis and usability testing.

Designed and developed retirement investing tools for 401k.com, Fidelity's website for institutional investors. Tools included the Contribution Calculator, Withdrawal Calculator and Take Home Pay Calculator.

Nicholas Hoyt

Education

B.A. in Computer Science, University of Massachusetts Boston, 1991 Summa cum laude

Introduction to Programming in Pascal, Harvard Extension School, 1988 Grade: A

Jazz Composition & Arranging major, Berklee College of Music, Boston, MA Seven full-time semesters, 1981–1984, GPA of 3.85/4.0

Skills

User Experience/Interaction Design

- · Requirements gathering and analysis
- Development of conceptual models, personas, scenarios
- Essential use cases, user role- and task-models
- · Creation of wireframes using Sketch, OmniGraffle and Figma

User Research & Information Architecture

- · Field observations, contextual interviews
- · Task-modeling workshops, wants and needs analysis
- Card sorting exercises, focus groups
- · Paper prototyping, low-fidelity prototypes

Usability Testing & Analysis

- Creation of interactive HTML/JavaScript prototypes
- · Facilitation of remote and lab-based usability testing
- · Quantitative and qualitative analysis of test results

Front-End Development

- · JavaScript, HTML, CSS, DOM scripting and event handling
- WCAG 2.0 accessibility requirements
- · Responsive design
- · Web components, WebExtensions API

Resources

Browser Extensions & Plugins

- Page Structure for Firefox
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Chrome
- SkipTo Landmarks & Headings for Firefox
- · A11yFirst plugins for CKEditor
- Alnspector for Firefox
- · Accessibility Bookmarklets